<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shivam Agarwal - scribing my thoughts</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/zfeed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 21:21:31 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 21:21:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The extended part of family</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me ask you a very direct question. Why do we need extended family? Here by extended family I mean all the blood relation except your parents and siblings. I have always thought of this but was never able to organize my thoughts before. Today I try that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Family in earlier times was considered as one where there is bond of love with a common lineage. But is that it? No. Family is the first point of contact where one goes for consultation. At least it was in earlier days. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I do not see that happenning. Now it has become nothing more than just a permanent guest list which is taken out of box only to send invites for certain occassions in life. But should be only like this? If yes then what is the purpose of maintaining the relations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions may be blunt but their realization is the first step towards correction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been so furious that inspite of having a large family, why there is no elder person to guide through various events of life. Whether it be academic, career or social. My goal is not to let this happen to younger generation. But how to achieve that when we have become so separate now? How to suggest something which is genuinely beneficial, without being perceived as beneficiary in some way? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seriously want to thank my Mamaji for suggesting and encouraging my mother a good education for me and my siblings. We cannot thank him enough. Because of the education only, we are today able to make ourselves independent financially. We cannot repay that debt ever and this is exactly my idea of a family - how it must be !!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/12/06/The-extended-part-of-family.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/12/06/The-extended-part-of-family.html</guid>
        
        <category>Extended part of family</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Lost Humanity</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What do we mean by the word humanity? Is it a way to describe acts of kindness towards another human/animal? What’s the word for cruelty towards the same then? And finally - shouldn’t humanity be the duty of a living being, necessary to co-exist?
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently visited Goa and simply loved the place. The city is so different than others in India. Everybody chills out without disturbing others. The experience of riding Scooty with friends on sea shores, having a dip in sea anytime you feel like and the awesome food makes you feel just like in heaven. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I had a very strange encounter with a situation which forced me to think. We were at Baga beach, enjoying the company of friends and good food. Around 1 AM, a poor family of three - mother, a little girl of 7 and an elder brother of 15 began to perform their stunts with fire. Everybody was mesmerized at the talent of the boy who was playing very easily with fire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the performance, he collected money and people settled down. Just then a person gave 100 bucks to the mother and forced the little girl to have a drink. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine the  situation. There were 15 occupied tables around 35 people on an average. Everybody watched the act, spared the change and settled again at their tables. But when the guy physically forced the little girl, no one was even bothered. I understand why the mother was not reacting as for her 100 bucks were more important than the dignity of her children. But why not others? 
Why didn’t anyone present there, react? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guy went on to put a solo chair in front of the little girl and asked her to dance. This went on for at least full 10 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we feel the inability to stand up against something utterly wrong in front of our own eyes? What holds us? Why don’t we have the strength to get up and do something? If we feel so helpless imagine the state of the victim and that too a little girl of 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See I am in no way a leader or an “inspirer”. I am still forming my own beliefs. I look out for inspiration and for someone to follow. But I am starting to feel like that there is no such person. Now I am starting to understand the true meaning of the famous poem “Invictus” by William E. Henley: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic; &quot;&gt;
Out of the night that covers me,  &lt;br /&gt;
Black as the pit From pole to pole, &lt;br /&gt;
I thank whatever gods may be &lt;br /&gt;
For my unconquerable soul. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In the fell clutch of circumstance &lt;br /&gt;
I have not winced nor cried aloud. &lt;br /&gt;
Under the bludgeonings of chance &lt;br /&gt;
My head is bloody, but unbowed. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Beyond this place of wrath and tears &lt;br /&gt;
Looms but the Horror of the shade, &lt;br /&gt;
And yet the menace of the years &lt;br /&gt;
Finds, and shall find, me unafraid. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It matters not how strait the gate, &lt;br /&gt;
How charged with punishments the scroll, &lt;br /&gt;
I am the master of my fate: &lt;br /&gt;
I am the captain of my soul. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The theme of this post should not be to understand how optimist or pessimist I am and judge me. Believe me, I will write other posts which will allow you to do so. I write this only in the spirit to highlight the fear we all have inside. It reminds me of a quote - &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight:600&quot;&gt;
&quot;Courage is not the absence of fear but rather the judgement that something is more important than fear; &lt;br /&gt;The brave may not live forever, but the cautious do not live at all.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After witnessing the inhumane acts of that guy for about 10 minutes, we went to handle the situation. I didn’t even talk to the guy. I took the family aside and talked to them. Told the mother that money was not that important (but then I don’t know the pain hunger brings). Reassured elder brother that what he has is an amazing talent and just believe in yourself, these days will be over soon. At this point the little girl who was standing by her brother said something to me. The emotion was so pure that I was unable to say anything after that. She said - “Thank you bhaiya!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think we uplift the life of beggar by giving some money? No. Because mostly we do it to get rid of the person from our face. The biggest gift we can give others is to believe in them and reassure them of hope.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/10/22/The-Lost-Humanity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/10/22/The-Lost-Humanity.html</guid>
        
        <category>humanity</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Random Thoughts - 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First thread:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t understand the way we think and make a mapping of certain things in our lives. It’s very interesting and shocking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there no party where food is not the central theme? Can we not engage ourselves in a party to do something constructive? Why do we think twice while helping out a poor guy but not even once while ordering another beer, even when we know we have had enough? :P, or while paying extra to make our journey a bit more comfortable? See the point is not to discourage the things we normally do according to whatever mapping we have. The point I want to emphasize is that have we accepted these mappings to be the only way? The result of which - have we stopped exploring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why exploration is important? It is because while exploring the unknown, we sometimes discover ourselves. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second thread:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t understand how people get alarmed and predict dangers of future when we spend Rs. 540/- for a humane act and are surprisingly normal when we are spending thousands on luxury, on clothes we have not worn in years or on the unhealthy food we very often eat? And to remind you unhealthy food not only harms economically but also financially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that I am in that phase of life where I consider every person wrong, other than me:P. I know that this too shall pass, but I am so eager to learn its answers when that happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third thread:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that I am not going to have enough money in life w.r.t. others. But here is what I know for sure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that I will have just enough to sustain a decent life. A life for me or family where there is no shortage of basic necessities. I also know that other people earning more than me will not disturb me ever (I am testing it now - so yeah results are pending :P), but not making my life worthy of living will definitely be major disturbance. And according to me a worthy life is one where you sometimes help lives of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fourth thread:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not consider myself introvert but I guess less social would be a better fit. The problem with being less social is that you are often lonely and advantage is that you are mostly alone!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/09/04/Random-Thoughts-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/09/04/Random-Thoughts-2.html</guid>
        
        <category>random thoughts</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Appreciation &amp; Motivation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What is appreciation and why is it necessary? Almost all of us need to be appreciated. Sometimes we desire it most for our particular work and from an important person in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it for a moment.An employee wants to be appreciated by their manager while discussing his/her rating, wives want to be appreciated by their husband, husbands want to be acknowledged after fixing an electrical crisis at home or for some other macho work, bachelor’s want to be appreciated by friends after buying a new luxurious piece of comfort and a daily wage worker wants to appreciate himself/herself that they survived another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post is about how we ourselves define our need of appreciation. The need of appreciation can originate from various reasons, including both good and bad ones. There is another aspect which I am feeling now. You sometimes do not know whether your works are good or bad. You expect, with your whole heart and soul that someone important to you should appreciate your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now hold on to this thought. Why I am eager to discover and think more about this feeling is because it is related to that time of our academics when in a very short time we suddenly lost interest in a subject. Think about it, whether there was any such moment in your life where you were good in a particular subject and in a very short time you suddenly lost it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did that happen because of the case where you did some work, which you didn’t know was worthy enough and were not appreciated? The result - did you gave up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of appreciation and motivation as the most important and the most powerful tools for a teacher. They are like uranium. The decision of how and when to use them can lead to either constructive or equally destructive consequences, just like an atomic plant or a nuclear bomb respectively. The only difference with these and a nuclear bomb is, not using them will also lead to a destructive event i.e. losing a student’s interest in a subject.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/09/04/Appreciation-&-Motivation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/09/04/Appreciation-&-Motivation.html</guid>
        
        <category>appreciation</category>
        
        <category>motivation</category>
        
        <category>reward</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Near Perfect Weekend</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time back I wrote about a discovery of a question that “What is a perfect weekend?”. At that time I discovered one aspect of it and this time I witnessed another one, which was absolutely mindblowing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weekend started with working in lab and getting all excited about my work. I had lots of idea which I will test out to find results. I thought about incorporating universe simulation data in Amit and my work on augmented nodetrix, showcasing halo catalogs as dense networks based on their certain properties and further study them through our matrix visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I got to spent the most awesome time with great friends. The best part - you get to eat lots of extremely good dishes when you have newly married friends. I guess they want to showcase their skills in cooking too :P. But they don’t know that the more they play hosts, more we feel as guests. Anyway I am extremely lucky to meet regularly and enjoy the delicacies prepared by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part is something which I know I will never forget. I was at Bangalore Central Mall near Jayadeva, catching up with a friend in Mc Donalds. Suddenly two kids of age probably 13 years came and asked for Rs. 10/- as donation towards Ganpati celebration in their locality. As all of us, my first reaction to neglect and asked them to go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five minutes later another another group of 3 kids, same age, came and asked for the same. This time I don’t know what struck in my mind, I took them outside and started asking them lots of questions - “Do you guys study?, Which standard? Subjects? What after class X? What they do in Ganpati celebration? How it benefits them? etc..”. I donated my share to first group and asked them whether they would like to have dosa, to which they happily agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So just outside Central Mall, there we were, 6 kids, Manjunath, Chand, Mallesh, Anil and two other names I couldn’t remember, having dosa and having wonderful time. I realized that these kids are happy in each other’s company, without complaining of their background. One of them lost his father and his mother works everyday as house keeping staff. Suddenly I noticed he was barefoot. I took a quick glance and observed another kid was also barefoot. I asked them would they like it, if I give them a pair of slippers, to which they happily agreed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now my friend Ankita also joined and became a part of our wonderful circle. So after finishing dosa, we went inside mall, searched for a nice pair of slippers and gave it to them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be very honest, this was something I have never witnessed. I would explain how. All of us know how people form opinions, judging through appearance (and it’s not their fault). The lady at entrance of mall first refused to let the kids enter. I persuaded that they were with me. As soon as I entered I felt scared - what if they steal something? So I turned back and saw them and believe me it was wonderful. Their body language gave me answer that I can trust them blindfold. Two were holding each other as they were very scared by thinking that the mall is so rich, people have so money and they will be somehow harmed. Three were inquisitive. They found the place to be awesome and wanted to know more, but still they held each other to ensure no one is lost in this “alien” world. I like the sixth one. He was not afraid of anything and confident to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this point I didn’t had any doubts. We searched for the place where they kept slippers. The salesman was very kind to help up find the right size. I was continuously surprised by these guys. The same guy who lost his father, was so well mannered that he insisted that he should carry slippers to the billing counter and not us. I am unable to write that scenario better in words, but his empotion was of respect towards us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We paid the bill, gave slippers to my wonderful, little friends and came outside mall. They were inquisitive in knowing about us. So they reciprocated my questions and asked me about my name, home town and what I do for a living. When we came out I told them this - “Don’t be astonished by the glamour you see in this mall. You guys can achieve much more than the people you see around now. Just promise to do two things for me - One, to never leave studies and regularly attend school. Second, never do a wrong deed.” We all hailed to that and said good bye. I will never forget the delight I saw in the eyes of my special and newest friends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and Ankita agreed on spliting the bill, so that we both can share the happiness we felt today!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/08/30/Near-Perfect-Weekend.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/08/30/Near-Perfect-Weekend.html</guid>
        
        <category>perfect weekend</category>
        
        <category>helping children</category>
        
        <category>good deeds</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Random Thoughts - 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Once in a while you get so many thoughts that you actually cannot understand whether what you are doing is right or wrong. There are such times when one wants something but in keeping long term goal in mind, one does not do anything towards it and sometimes its just plain laziness. :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think happiness is an extremely quantifiable and subjective quantity. A child is happy when given a chocolate, but it doubles when given two. We grown ups are so much caught up in today’s 3 x 5 inch screen that we are always busy without any work. It is tempting me to measure the amount of time I waste when I install all the travel, shopping and entertainment apps. The disturbance is not from having them, but from their constant reminders which pop up every now and then saying - “hello, we apps exist!!”. I am thinking to shutdown my smartphone for a few days just to realize whether it is productive or not. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of spending this birthday in a bit different manner. Will keep you updated!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/08/28/Random-Thoughts-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/08/28/Random-Thoughts-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>random thoughts</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lot of things going on in life. With the end of Masters course, comes a time to take some hard decisions. Decisions which builds you, challenge and define you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a  question. Getting a job in any company(general) will eventually define the path of your career. The work you will be assigned there, the strategy company management will take and the path decided by others will create the need of work which eventually you will end up doing right now. So the question is, how to leave one’s career decision on somene’s else’s motives and luck?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question is driving me to think seriously towards a higher degree through which I eventually want to achieve some independence towards achieving my goal in life. There is another feeling which is driving me to stay in campus for some more time. I still feel a bit gap left in M. Tech. education which I want to fulfill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If doing mistakes made anyone rich, I would be by now the richest man alive. I think making mistakes is a luxury which everybody cannot afford. But repeating them is foolishness and learning from them is experience. &lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/16/PhD.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/16/PhD.html</guid>
        
        <category>PhD.</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trapped Outside - few lines by me.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While I was preparing for GATE examination 2 years back, I wrote few lines. These lines describes the effort I was able to put in. Today I stumbled on it and thought to share. So here are the lines which kept me going:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight:600&quot;&gt;TRAPPED  OUTSIDE &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic;&quot;&gt;

With all the time in world, &lt;br /&gt;
yet no time to be. &lt;br /&gt;
a long road lies ahead &lt;br /&gt;
and there's no one but me. &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
sentenced for time with a hope of trail &lt;br /&gt;
been trapped outside in a barless jail &lt;br /&gt;
what binds me are not physical chains &lt;br /&gt;
but a question- What you are going to be? &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
World's a strange place to be &lt;br /&gt;
a lot are wet in rain while others enjoy their hot tea &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
It's not that bad at all you see, &lt;br /&gt;
coz it gives a fair chance to thee &lt;br /&gt;
we can either complain &quot;i had a great fall&quot; &lt;br /&gt;
or can rise again like tides of sea. &lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;
So I rise again and say this- &lt;br /&gt;
&quot;I stand tall, and you try make me fall.&lt;br /&gt;
give it your best and &lt;br /&gt; 
  &lt;br /&gt; 
              CHALLENGE ME !!!! &quot; &lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/06/Trapped-Outside.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/06/Trapped-Outside.html</guid>
        
        <category>Poem</category>
        
        <category>Optimism</category>
        
        <category>Determination</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Poem by my father</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My elder brother got married last year in the month of January. At that time I made a &lt;a href=&quot;http://shivam-hello.appspot.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;website &lt;/a&gt; for them ( -sorry for the website name my purchased dns expired :P). My father recalled a beautiful poem and asked to add it to the site. I do not remember how it skipped my mind, but I forgot to do so. … &lt;!-- more --&gt;
Today suddenly I realized it, searched my mail for half an hour and volla found it. Now I remember why I didn’t add to website at that time. Reason - it was in Hindi and I didn’t knew how to write in any language other than English on web :P . Now I do. So without further adieu, here is the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;poem  for bhaiya and bhabhi :&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;hindi&quot;&gt;
आख़िर हम सब की खोज पूरी हुई |  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

खुशी के इन लम्हों में किसी शायर की लिखी हुई कुछ पंक्तियाँ याद आ रही है : &lt;br /&gt;
 
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center hindi&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight:600&quot;&gt;

&quot; रिश्तों का रूप बदलता है, &lt;br /&gt;
बुनियादें ख़त्म नहीं होती |  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
ख्वाबों की ओर उमंगों की &lt;br /&gt;
मियादें ख़त्म नहीं होती |&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
इक फूल में तेरा रूप बसा &lt;br /&gt;
इक फूल में मेरी जवानी है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
इक चेहरा तेरी निशानी है &lt;br /&gt;
इक चेहरा मेरी निशानी है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
तुझको - मुझको जीवन अमृत &lt;br /&gt;
अब इन हाथों से पीना है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
इनकी धड़कन में बसना है &lt;br /&gt;
इनकी साँसों में पीना है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
तू अपनी अदायें बक्शइन्हें &lt;br /&gt;
मैं अपनी वफ़ायें देता हूँ | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
जो अपने लिए सोची थी कभी &lt;br /&gt;
वो सारी दुआएँ देता हूँ |&quot; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;hindi&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right; font-weight:600;&quot;&gt; - राजीव अग्रवाल &lt;br /&gt;
	(Recollected from a famous one) &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/images/poem.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/poem_thumbnail.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/01/Poem-by-my-father.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/01/Poem-by-my-father.html</guid>
        
        <category>Poem</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is a perfect weekend?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sounds bizarre. What is a perfect weekend? How do you quantify a weekend? How do you take into account different perspectives of people? …
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
Well you don’t. This post is going to be about how you can try something different and at last speak -“That was a perfect weekend!”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, as many of us are, spent almost a year in Bangalore with watching movies/videos and/or facebook/youtube on weekends. And now I can tell you that I was a big idiot to spend them like that. After getting bored being in a room, went and watched movies in malls, had meals in restaurants etc. I gotta admit, being with friends is a lot of fun. So yeah the second way was more fun. Then I came across a third way to spend them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never be able to thank Amit and Pankaj enough for introducing me to running and exercising respectively :P. They helped to discover a third way to spend and make a weekend perfect. The idea is damn simple: BE ACTIVE !!!. That’s it. That is my great discovery. So rudimentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just for a second do the math: how much do we spend on a movie and a follow up with meal in restaurant? And during this time how much time are we really connecting with each other? And now think how much interaction is there in any team sport. That’s my point: if you are spending the same amount in different activity which gives you more time interacting and having fun with friends, then which one should we choose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice is really yours. But as an experiment try something different this weekend and feel the difference. Just for a start and to reduce cost: have a swim with friends in society pool, play table tennis/cricket/football, do cycling and the best one - go for a running in group. You won’t believe how much fun you’ll have running with friends. Just for some inspiration - discover more about Ironman triathlon which happens every year in Hawai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop procrastinating, be active and really connect with your dear friends !!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/25/What-is-a-perfect-weekend%3F.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/25/What-is-a-perfect-weekend%3F.html</guid>
        
        <category>Stay Active</category>
        
        <category>Running</category>
        
        <category>Sports</category>
        
        <category>Swimming</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
