<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shivam Agarwal - scribing my thoughts</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/zfeed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 18:17:37 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 18:17:37 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Poem by my father</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My elder brother got married last year in the month of January. At that time I made a website for them. My father wrote a beautiful poem and asked to add it to the site. I do not remember how it skipped my mind, but I forgot to do so. Today suddenly I realized it, searched my mail for half an hour and volla found it. Now I remember why I didn’t add to website at that time. Reason - it was in Hindi and I didn’t knew how to write in any language other than English on web :P . Now I do. So without further adieu, here is the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;poem by my father for bhaiya and bhabhi :&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;hindi&quot;&gt;
आख़िर हम सब की खोज पूरी हुई |  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

खुशी के इन लम्हों में किसी शायर की लिखी हुई कुछ पंक्तियाँ याद आ रही है : &lt;br /&gt;
 
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center hindi&quot; style=&quot;font-style: italic; font-weight:600&quot;&gt;

&quot; रिश्तों का रूप बदलता है, &lt;br /&gt;
बुनियादें ख़त्म नहीं होती |  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
ख्वाबों की ओर उमंगों की &lt;br /&gt;
मियादें ख़त्म नहीं होती |&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
इक फूल में तेरा रूप बसा &lt;br /&gt;
इक फूल में मेरी जवानी है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
इक चेहरा तेरी निशानी है &lt;br /&gt;
इक चेहरा मेरी निशानी है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
तुझको - मुझको जीवन अमृत &lt;br /&gt;
अब इन हाथों से पीना है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
इनकी धड़कन में बसना है &lt;br /&gt;
इनकी साँसों में पीना है | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
तू अपनी अदायें बक्शइन्हें &lt;br /&gt;
मैं अपनी वफ़ायें देता हूँ | &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
जो अपने लिए सोची थी कभी &lt;br /&gt;
वो सारी दुआएँ देता हूँ |&quot; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;hindi&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right; font-weight:600;&quot;&gt; - राजीव अग्रवाल &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/images/poem.jpeg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/poem_thumbnail.jpeg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/01/Poem-by-my-father.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/06/01/Poem-by-my-father.html</guid>
        
        <category>Poem</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is a perfect weekend?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sounds bizarre. What is a perfect weekend? How do you quantify a weekend? How do you take into account different perspectives of people? …
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
Well you don’t. This post is going to be about how you can try something different and at last speak -“That was a perfect weekend!”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, as many of us are, spent almost a year in Bangalore with watching movies/videos and/or facebook/youtube on weekends. And now I can tell you that I was a big idiot to spend them like that. After getting bored being in a room, went and watched movies in malls, had meals in restaurants etc. I gotta admit, being with friends is a lot of fun. So yeah the second way was more fun. Then I came across a third way to spend them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never be able to thank Amit and Pankaj enough for introducing me to running and exercising respectively :P. They helped to discover a third way to spend and make a weekend perfect. The idea is damn simple: BE ACTIVE !!!. That’s it. That is my great discovery. So rudimentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just for a second do the math: how much do we spend on a movie and a follow up with meal in restaurant? And during this time how much time are we really connecting with each other? And now think how much interaction is there in any team sport. That’s my point: if you are spending the same amount in different activity which gives you more time interacting and having fun with friends, then which one should we choose?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The choice is really yours. But as an experiment try something different this weekend and feel the difference. Just for a start and to reduce cost: have a swim with friends in society pool, play table tennis/cricket/football, do cycling and the best one - go for a running in group. You won’t believe how much fun you’ll have running with friends. Just for some inspiration - discover more about Ironman triathlon which happens every year in Hawai.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop procrastinating, be active and really connect with your dear friends !!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/25/What-is-a-perfect-weekend%3F.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/25/What-is-a-perfect-weekend%3F.html</guid>
        
        <category>Stay Active</category>
        
        <category>Running</category>
        
        <category>Sports</category>
        
        <category>Swimming</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Run Forrest Run ....</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;para-center&quot; style=&quot;font-style:italic;&quot;&gt;

Once upon a time, there was a child&lt;br /&gt;

a bit lethargic, thinking - &quot;will this unwind?&quot; ...&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In every PE class he sat on stands,&lt;br /&gt;
while others ran fast, he gave glance&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;

Noone cared what was he missing,&lt;br /&gt;
coz everytime he ran, his heart was pounding&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;

Years went by and he also didn't care&lt;br /&gt;
there was much to do, he thought&lt;br /&gt;
and said, &quot;at least I am breathing same air&quot;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;

nine years went by, he didn't care&lt;br /&gt;
And one day, a friend said&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;I will run beside you, atleast try&quot;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;

Then he ran with friend for the first time&lt;br /&gt;
he was happy even with 15 min. a mile !!!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah that child is me. For almost my entire life I was not able to run for even 600 meters without gasping for air. But now I am so happy and thankful to the friend to make me realize the fun in running. Earlier I saw some running events in my hometown and I used to think- “what are they doing?”. On 17 May 2015, for the first time I became “they”. I ran 6 km in TCS Bangalore run. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt so amazing that I cannot describe it in words. The people had awesome energy. People of every age group were running with each other, telling all the way to keep going and not to stop. Result? Everybody, I mean everyone there, inspite of their body condition, completed the run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess that’s the power of optimism. It influences more if it comes from other person. There’s a quote - &lt;strong&gt;“You don’t see the world as it is, you see it, as you are.”&lt;/strong&gt; I have been an audience of running event as well as a participant and the experience of both is world’s apart. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue running because it regenerates optimism and recharges with positive energy. And I guess those are enough ingredients to achieve any dream. Isn’t it? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S.: You don’t believe it? Give it a try … &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;para-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/running_pic.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/21/Run-Forest-Run.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/21/Run-Forest-Run.html</guid>
        
        <category>Running</category>
        
        <category>Optimism</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EFFORTLESS DOING - is there such a thing ?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading a book titled &lt;strong&gt;“The Tao of Pooh” by Benjamin Hoff&lt;/strong&gt;. The book beautifully describes the concept of &lt;strong&gt;effortless doing&lt;/strong&gt;. In other words, &lt;strong&gt;doing something without overdoing&lt;/strong&gt;. It relates the concepts of Taoism with a very old cartoon of Winnie the Pooh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the idea of Taoism and even more I loved the way author related it to the cartoon. I think people who really liked the cartoon of Winnie the pooh will surely be amazed when they read the relation author makes. It gives a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to share in this article is the thought that is the principle of &lt;strong&gt;“effortless doing”&lt;/strong&gt; practically possible in a country like India? Recently I went to a wedding of a friend. Rituals spanned the whole night. Just to get some fresh air I went outside at 6 o clock in morning. I was surprised at first to see children of 11 and 12 standard all dressed with packed up lunch boxes, driving their bicycle going for studies at such an early hour. They won’t return to their homes for atleast 11 hours. 3 hours of coaching in morning followed by 7 hours of school and then again 2 hours classes after that.
It is damn hectic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why I say this is to get a better understanding of principles of Taoism. Some questions linger in my mind, like &lt;strong&gt;is the concept of effortless doing not applicable in age group of students?&lt;/strong&gt; specially in a place which is overflowing with competition? Or is it only for certain class and age of people in society? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the answers of them yet, but I think I will find them out eventually and hoping effortlessly!! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/18/Effortless-doing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/18/Effortless-doing.html</guid>
        
        <category>Taoism</category>
        
        <category>Effortless Doing</category>
        
        <category>Benjamin hoff</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teaching - Professionalism vs. Passion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I wrote the article a year back while pondering over quality and areas of improvement in education system. Apparently many people think that educational system needs improvement and I am no exception to that. I wrote the following as an open letter which expresses my opinion and feelings. I think in future I’ll agree with some points and disagree with others…
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I address this letter to all the highly qualified faculties, which have changed several
things in their lifetime for betterment of society. I address this letter to all the
authorities present in education system who are responsible to manage and run them.
I address this letter to teachers, principals, professors, deans, directors, registrars and
retired teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask authorities to pause for a moment. Please, just for a moment stop thinking about
the works you have done. Now look at the education system we have collectively
built. What kind of education system we continue to build? Yes there have been some
students who have shown exceptional performance and made us all proud. But is this
the true potential of a country with more than 1.2 billion people? Won’t you agree that the number of
exceptional students are extremely less when compared to total population of our
country? If it is, than doesn’t it indicate that we are doing something or maybe
somethings wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I had a long chat with an integrated M.Tech student (which comprises of 5
years) studying in 5th semester. At exactly the halftime of total course duration. I am
an engineer from a University which is at level three in our country. I am from
UPTU. Back then I considered that all UPTU colleges are like this only and situation
is better in IIT’s, IIIT’s and NIT’s. But today I was forced to rethink.
I understand that having a chat with just one student is too small sample size, but it
raises questions in me which are very general in nature.
What should we teach to a person or a kid, in professional courses like B.tech or
integrated M.Tech of 4 and 5 years respectively?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with course syllabus. What is the objective of keeping a subject insyllabus? If you answer that it should be to teach or to make student understand the
basics of it, then I’ll be very sorry to say that we are terribly failing at it. Our
evaluation criteria is such that we do not get to know whether a student has
understood the basics of a subject or not. Students pass with almost same
marks/grades, either they understand the basics or not. I am not raising question on
why to keep that subject in the course. My question is, in such environment what
difference it is making to keep it in syllabus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may sound an idealist, but oppose me if you don’t agree with me on this - why a
question paper should not have a question like what did you learn in this subject?
Where you think, you can apply the understandings based on the subject? What
difference you think it will make in your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To evaluate whether a student has understood a subject or not, is a question paper and
answer sheet the only way ? Why not ask students to explain the subject as they have
understood, to a dummy person and ask appropriate questions verbally where
required? Isn’t this the world wide adopted strategy to judge a person before
recruiting for a critical job position?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evaluation of students is just one part which I want to highlight. I ask you now the
other question. Should the subjects in a course be the only things to be learned by kids of 18-20
years of age? I stress on this question with extreme importance. Guys, lets think for a
moment here. We have a job i.e. to run the educational system. For it we make a
commitment that I teacher of XYZ subject is responsible to teach XYZ subject only.
This is what is happening. My question is, is this correct?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is right, then from where do we expect students to learn other important things
of life? We keep those courses which have professional importance, but from where do we expect students to learn moral values? From where a student will learn not to
think of a life dependent on salary of job but a life dependent on principles and
values? From where a student will learn bravery to pursue his/her own interests even
if those interests are not directly related to the professional course in which he/she in
currently enrolled? From where a student will build a brave and strong core, which
will lead towards a peaceful life and act as a source of light which can enlighten
others, even after death?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just have one last question for everybody - Is it not the case that great personalities
in history have understood and learned the answer of last question I ask?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/17/Teaching-professionalism-vs-passion.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/17/Teaching-professionalism-vs-passion.html</guid>
        
        <category>Teaching</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Write a program to check for a Leap Year. Sounds easy right?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am sure everyone has at least once witnessed a complex system which always seem to be a very simple one. We take these simple systems for granted and assume that this is how it must work. But digging deeper in the history we often find something which is amazing and shakes our entire understanding of the system. &lt;strong&gt;Gregorian calender&lt;/strong&gt; system is one such system. How? Let’s find out…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An year, in very simple terms, can be said as that time period which Earth takes to complete one full revolution around the Sun. We found that one year is around &lt;strong&gt;365 and one-fourth days&lt;/strong&gt;. To adjust this one fourth day, we added one full day to every fourth year. This was the basis of &lt;strong&gt;Julian calender system&lt;/strong&gt; which existed before 1752.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to be precise one year is 365.2424 days. So whenever we were celebrating the new year day, Earth covered a little more path in it’s elliptical path, than one complete revolution. This small change accumulates and becomes a difference of 11 days in about 1600 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the difference of 11 days means? It means whatever the Earth’s position is it today, it will be ahead of it by 11 days in about full 1600 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this lead to some discrepancy among various religions when to celebrate their occasions as some followed moon’s cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to correct this and save future trouble some decisions were made in year 1752. &lt;strong&gt;If you are hearing them for the first time, you’ll be amazed to know it.&lt;/strong&gt; They are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pope said in a stern voice (I am being dramatic here)- “Erase these eleven days as we are already ahead according to the time of year”. And hence eleven days from September month of year 1752 were erased. Dates from 3rd September to 13th September 1752 don’t exist. Surprised? It’s true.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pope also said that from now on only those years will be leap years who are divisible by 4 or by 400. Century years that are divisible by 100 but not by 400 will not be leap years.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think pope was a mathematician or he had an advisor who was good in mathematics. I say this because giving this rule of calculating leap years ensured that we will not fall into the same trouble in future again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How? Let’s see…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to rule 2 above, calculate how many days there will be in 400 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Thought process….&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm, in 400 years there will be 100 leap years according to old definition, but then I have to cancel those century years which are not divisible by 400, there are 3 such century years in a range of 400 years. So volla, in 400 years number of leap years are- 97 LEAP YEARS. &lt;strong&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total days in 400 years (According to calender) = 400*365 + 97 = 146097 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we know that one year consists of 365.2424 days. How many days in 400 years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total days in 400 years (According to observation)= 400*365.2424 = 146096.96 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes almost same with a difference of 0.04 day in 400 years. That’s bearable. And hence the law was signed to bring the rules in effect immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know, this sounds bizarre right? But this is how it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you still have some doubts, read this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a cal command in linux systems which gives calender of years in range 1 to 9999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check for year 100&lt;/strong&gt;. You will find it as a leap year because the new rule was implemented in 1752.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need something more? &lt;strong&gt;Check calender of year 1752 and look for September month&lt;/strong&gt;. You’ll find 11 days missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also to support what I have said, calculate this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got the difference of 0.04 days in 400 years. In how many years will this difference be of one full day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years for difference of 1 day = 400/0.04 = 10,000 years. And that is the range of cal command because it hasn’t been decided where to put this one more extra day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be force with you!!!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/computer%20articles/2015/05/16/Leap-year.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/computer%20articles/2015/05/16/Leap-year.html</guid>
        
        <category>Gregorian Calender</category>
        
        <category>Leap Year</category>
        
        <category>Calender</category>
        
        
        <category>computer articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>One Month Remaining in College</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Exactly one month from today, our work in IIIT-B will be officially finished. Farewell from any place brings a lot of memories and thoughts. Thoughts which lead a person to fetch answers of some questions like - how fruitful it was, what next etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I am tied up in my thesis work and have to finish it with full zeal and concentration. Though I have not done very significant amount of work, it surely has removed the fear of few subjects. For this I will be very thankful to my supervisor and friends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/15/One-month-remaining-in-college.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/general/2015/05/15/One-month-remaining-in-college.html</guid>
        
        <category>Masters</category>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thinking Neumannically? Think again ...</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;i7 processors having 2.7 GHz clock speed, boosted to 3.3 GHz. Means in one second 3300000000 clock cycles are executed, capable of executing 92 billion instructions per second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It certainly leaves you with a chill feeling. Isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we ever imagine that so much is going on when we simply do a “quick” check of our facebook account and that too several times a day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is going to be about the most basic element which started the revolution of Digital Computers…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;- Have you ever wondered that in the name &lt;strong&gt;John von Neumann&lt;/strong&gt;, von starts with a small case v?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my great teachers always says – “Tum dekhta hai par dekhta nai”, means we see but we don’t observe. The question above stands a testimony of the quote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While building EDVAC (Electronic Discrete Variable Automatic Computer, a computer weighing 7850 kg.), an architecture was proposed as von Neumann Architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now why are we discussing an architecture that was introduced over 60 years ago? Because, even today you pick any desktop computer and it still uses the same architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John von Neumann was a great mathematician. As the greatest inventions have simplest underlying principle, von Neumann architecture is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It says that program and data reside in same memory. There is a connection between CPU and memory (RAM), called bus. At a time CPU can either be fetching/writing data or fetching an instruction from memory. It’s simple right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re an Undergraduate in Computer Science, I bet some bells must be ringing in your mind. I’ll give you a hint, it’s called – &lt;strong&gt;“Universal Turing Machine”&lt;/strong&gt;, which reads data from memory (through a memory tape) executed it and again writes back the result in memory. It’s not just a coincidence for two concepts so similar to emerge in near about the same time. Many of us don’t know but Alan Turing and John von Neumann worked together to shape the computers as we see them today. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to the von Neumann architecture, we still use it with some modifications. Like cache has been inserted to get better speed. But that too is only a modification since at a time processor can either fetch an instruction or fetch/write data. So what’s so great about it that we still use it (no offense to sir Neumann). It’s simplicity of performing either of the tasks is the main reason why it’s still used. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a computer where Instructions reside in different memory and data in a different one (this is Harvard architecture). The problem will be when to select what has to be done and then the selection would itself require some computation to be done which would again be performed by the same CPU. This complexity has forced processor makers to think in terms of Neumann architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious question would be that if there is only a single bus, wouldn’t it be a drawback in terms of speed? Definitely yes!! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The term “von Neumann bottleneck” was coined by John Backus in his 1977 ACM Turing Award lecture.&lt;/strong&gt; According to Backus:
&lt;cite&gt;
“Surely there must be a less primitive way of making big changes in the store than by pushing vast numbers of words back and forth through the von Neumann bottleneck. Not only is this tube a literal bottleneck for the data traffic of a problem, but, more importantly, it is an intellectual bottleneck that has kept us tied to word-at-a-time thinking instead of encouraging us to think in terms of the larger conceptual units of the task at hand. Thus programming is basically planning and detailing the enormous traffic of words through the von Neumann bottleneck, and much of that traffic concerns not significant data itself, but where to find it.”&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it simpler, we all know about instruction set and simple C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we want to add two numbers. The c statement will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c = a + b;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where a, b, c are variables.
Finally it will be converted into a sequence of instructions such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LDA  a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADD b&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;STA  c&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further will be converted to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DR -&amp;gt; M[a]   //DR- data register M[a]- stands for memory reference at address a. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AC -&amp;gt; DR         // AC – accumulator register &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DR -&amp;gt; M[b]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AC -&amp;gt; AC + DR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M[c] -&amp;gt; AC&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observe that at one time either the data or an instruction (such as addition) is fetched from memory (and hence the Neumann architecture). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means computer has to perform tasks serially? Yes, it performs tasks serially at this level. But today parallelism is achieved today using computers based on von Neumann architectures in a different way through threads and employing multiple processors in a system. You can find a great practical article here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from our previous program we can see how von Neumann architecture forces high level language developers to think in Neumann way. Read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~crary/819-f09/Backus78.pdf&quot;&gt;“this”&lt;/a&gt; article and you will be amazed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are systems build on Harvard architecture. But due to the concept of Cache memory we use today (which is modified Harvard architecture), the Harvard architecture is of little practical use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion John von Neumann was a great administrator too, coz he employed the greatest administration rule, which was &lt;strong&gt;Keep It Short and Simple&lt;/strong&gt;, unlike this article. :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh I almost forgot to answer: &lt;strong&gt;why v is in small case in the name John von Neumann?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is- &lt;strong&gt;go GOOGLE it!!&lt;/strong&gt;  Self learning is the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be force with you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further Read &lt;a href=&quot;http://qss.stanford.edu/~godfrey/vonNeumann/vnedvac.pdf&quot;&gt;“The First Draft Report on the EDVAC”&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/computer%20articles/2015/05/10/Thinking-Neumannically%3F-Think-again.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://shivam-agarwal.github.io/computer%20articles/2015/05/10/Thinking-Neumannically%3F-Think-again.html</guid>
        
        <category>John von Neumann</category>
        
        <category>von Neumann Architecture</category>
        
        <category>Universal Turing Machine</category>
        
        
        <category>computer articles</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
